# Edward E Griebel Jr.

edgriebel@gmail.com • http://www.edgriebel.com/ https://github.com/edgriebel • https://linkedin.com/in/edgriebel

#### **SUMMARY**

Full Stack Java architect, developer, and consultant, specializing in Java/Oracle/JavaScript solutions and integrations.

*Technical Specialties*: Java, J2EE/JavaEE, SQL, PL/SQL, JavaScript, CSS, JMS, jQuery, jQuery UI, RabbitMQ, Oracle, Cognos, JBoss, WebLogic, AppDynamics.

*Business Specialties*: Agile team leadership, customer-focused development, requirements gathering and analysis, technical liaison, systems integration, business intelligence

PROFESSIONAL WORK EXPERIENCE

# **Rochester Institute of Technology**

Rochester, New York, USA

Adjunct Professor

■ Instructor for Introduction to Java course (*ISTE-120*) for Fall 2017 semester.

## Paychex, Inc

Rochester, New York, USA

Middleware Architect

June 2013 – Present

August 2017 – Present

- Creating a system to rebalance 20,000 databases between 200 compute servers in the cloud. The goal is to maximize density by reducing cost while minimizing overall spikes in usage that affect customers' experience. Using algorithmic, statistical, and machine learning techniques including TensorFlow, Pandas, NumPy, and scikit-learn in Python.
- Created an internal IT Inventory system in HTML5/JavaScript/Java/RabbitMQ to provide single source
  of truth and display relationships between virtual and physical hosts, JVM/CLR runtimes, databases, and
  middleware infrastructure.
- Lead developer on system to gather and present metrics from hosts, JVMs, and middleware components, used to send alerts for problems and provide a single location to view runtime metrics.
- Created tools in Python to automate configuration and installation of AppDynamics on thousands of Weblogic servers using Weblogic WLST scripting tool.
- Member of cross-functional team for selection, prototyping, and implementation of AppDynamics application monitoring tool.

Technologies: Java, JavaScript, JQuery-UI, Oracle PL/SQL, Scikit-Learn, TensorFlow, Python, middleware, AppDynamics, Application Performance Monitoring, ClearCase, Ant, Git, JUnit, Vagrant

## Axeda, Inc (division of PTC)

Rochester, New York, USA

Senior Software Engineer, R&D

June 2010 – June 2013

- Full stack Java/Oracle/ActiveMQ JMS developer for IoT system.
- Lead for Cognos Business Intelligence integration with IoT data. Integrated Groovy with Cognos to script report creation, execution, publishing, and administration.
- Internal consulting for new and existing solutions for professional services and product management teams.

Technologies: Java, JavaScript, JBoss, Oracle PL/SQL, Hudson/Jenkins, JUnit, Cognos, Business Intelligence, Maven, SVN

Paychex, Inc

Rochester, New York, USA

Lead Developer

March 2005 – June 2010

- Development lead for team converting two existing Java/JSP/Oracle public-facing applications to HTML5 with YUI JavaScript library
- Development lead for team that created new public-facing Java web application to enable customers to directly enter employee information that previously required manual intervention and re-keying.
- Mentored new developers and delivered technical training to extended development team.
- Member of architecture team to research and set five-year strategy for web application strategy.

Technologies: Java, JavaScript, JSP, Struts, WebLogic, Oracle PL/SQL, Hudson/Jenkins, JUnit, clearCase, Ant

### **Frontier Communications**

Rochester, New York, USA

Senior Software Developer

November 2001 - March 2005

- Created Java web application to build and troubleshoot DSL circuits via vendor's SOAP API.
- Maintained Java/Oracle web application that tracked and displayed commissions for 600 salespeople.
- Completely automated weekly generation of 20 Excel spreadsheets containing partitioned sales data from EssBase Data Warehouse saving \$250,000 annually in personnel costs.
- Implemented CruiseControl for Continuous Integration of Java projects.

Technologies: Java, JSP, Struts, Oracle PL/SQL, Continuous Integration, JUnit, Excel VBA, EssBase Data Warehouse, Ant

## **Global Crossing** (division of Level3)

Rochester, New York, USA

Senior Software Developer

March 1999 – November 2001

- Development lead for multi-site team creating Java application to reconcile data network devices with order entry systems.
- Development lead for Perl CGI application to automatically create data circuits on ATM and Frame Relay data networks, saving users ten minutes per circuit.

Technologies: Perl, CGI, Java, Sybase, Solaris, Ant

JP Morgan

New York, New York, USA June 1995 – February 1999

Lead Developer

- Created trading systems and calculation engines in C and C++.
- Implemented processes and applications for position tracking for derivatives High-Frequency Trading desk.

Technologies: C, C++, Sybase, Excel VBA, ClearCase

## **EDUCATION** Bucknell University

Lewisburg, Pennsylvania, USA

B.S. in Computer Engineering

- Senior design project creating reference implementation of DHCP protocol for RFCs 1531 and 1534
- Summer research internship in digital image processing
- Concentrations in Geology and Digital Electronics

Technologies: Computer Science, C, VAX assembly, DHCP, TCP-IP, Digital Electronics

# **CERTIFICATIONS AppDynamics Certified Implementations Professional**

November 2016

"An individual who attains the AppDynamics Certified Implementation Professional certification has demonstrated that he or she possesses the minimum acceptable level of knowledge and skills required to deploy AppDynamics Controllers, Agents, EUM Servers and Analytics Servers. This individual also has experience using AppDynamics APIs to extend and customize the AppDynamics platform."

# PRESENTATION AND MENTORING EXPERIENCE

## **Adjunct Lecturer**

Fall 2017

Rochester Institute of Technology

Lecturer for a class of 30 undergraduate and graduate students for the course ISTE-120, an introduction to Java course for Information Science and Technology majors.

## **Summer Co-Op Mentor**

Summer 2015

Paychex, Inc.

After interviewing a number of students, our team brought on a college student for three months. During that time I mentored them on their development tasks, our software development life cycle, version control, and working on a real-world development team. During this time I had the opportunity to give feedback on code, show how things learned in the classroom apply to corporate development, and work through actual software engineering problems.

# Axeda Reporting – A Guide to Service Intelligence (Presentation)

May 2013

Axeda Connection Conference, Axeda, Inc.

Live presentation for Axeda customers to review and demonstrate new features added to the Cognos big data reporting product.

## Java Technical Lead and Team Lead

2005 - 2010

Pavchex. Inc.

- As one of the technical leads for Java, developers on the extended team would come to me when they had deep technical questions about their code or odd errors that they couldn't track down. I would also have conversations with experienced developers to determine the "best" solution for a problem that would meet given technical or scheduling constraints.
- The department I was in created training exercises for new developers to introduce them to the tools and development environment. I worked with each new developer to review their answers to the Java exercises, answer questions as they worked through them, and working through topics new to them.
- I gave quarterly presentations to the extended team to introduce Java technologies and internal systems. Topics included web application redesigns and base functionality, Java JSP and servlet development, and web testing techniques.

As a Java team lead, I was responsible for a small team of developers. Since this was the first job after college for some, as we reviewed their code I would see opportunities to mentor them on advanced Java and JavaScript concepts and topics.

# AWARDS AppDynamics Scale Award, AppSphere 2015

November 2015

Awarded to the company that was able to quickly deploy the AppDynamics tool across the most complex environment. Our team deployed the AppDynamics tool to over 2,000 JBoss, WebLogic, and Windows IIS servers across production and non-production environments.

#### PUBLICATIONS TECHNICAL EDITOR

Reece, Richard M. *Oracle Certified Associate, Java SE 7 Programmer Study Guide*, Packt Publishing, 2012 Gonzalez, Javier Fernandez. *Java 7 Concurrency Cookbook*, Packt Publishing, 2012

OTHER Boy Scout and Cub Scout Leader ACTIVITIES FAA Certified Private Pilot

2007 – Present 2000

[CV compiled on 2018-03-07]